Have you ever dreamt of a better version of yourself?
The Substance is a horror, science fiction, thriller
film directed by Coralie Fargeat.
A fading celebrity decides to use a black market drug, a cell-replicating
substance that temporarily creates a younger, better version of herself.
Elisabeth, played by Demi Moore.
Sue, played by Margaret Qualley.
Harvey, played by Dennis Quaid.
Fred, played by Edward Hamilton-Clark.
Oliver, played by Gore Abrams.
Troy, played by Oscar Lesage.
The Substance is a 2024 body horror film written, directed,
co-produced, and co-edited by Coralie Fargeat.
It stars Demi Moore, Margaret Qualley, and Dennis Quaid.
The film follows a fading celebrity who is fired by her producer due to her age, and uses a black
market drug that creates a younger version of herself with unexpected side effects.
Fargeat wrote the screenplay to explore societal
pressures on women's bodies and aging.
A co-production between France, the United Kingdom, and the United States,
principal photography took place in France from August to October 2022.
Noted for its satirical elements and grotesque, hyperrealistic imagery, the film extensively utilised prosthetic makeup and
other practical effects such as suits, puppets, dummies, inserts, and approximately 21,000 liters (5,500 U.S.
gallons) of fake blood.
It was originally set to be distributed by Universal Pictures, but the rights were later acquired by Mubi after
Universal cancelled the distribution deal following a dispute with Fargeat over final cut privileges.
The Substance premiered at the 77th Cannes Film Festival on May 19, 2024, where
it won Best Screenplay and was nominated for the Palme d'Or.
The film was theatrically released in the United Kingdom and the United
States on September 20, 2024, and in France on November 6, 2024.
It received widespread acclaim, with particular praise for Fargeat's writing
and directing, the special effects, and Moore's performance.
At the box office, the film grossed $77–82 million on a budget of
$18 million, becoming Mubi's highest-grossing film.
Among numerous other accolades, it won the Academy Award for Best Makeup and Hairstyling and Moore's performance earned her a Golden Globe
Award, Critics' Choice Award, and Screen Actors Guild Award, as well as nominations for an Academy Award and BAFTA Award.
The film also received nominations for Best Picture and Best Director at
the Academy Awards, Critics’ Choice and Golden Globes.
The film explores themes of new year's eve,
capitalism, birthday, black market, identity.
The tone is dark and thought_provoking and intense.